A Guide to the Records of the Policy Office: Extraditions and Writs of Habeas Corpus of Governor Lawrence Douglas Wilder, 1990-1993
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Policy Office: Extraditions and Writs of Habeas Corpus of Governor Lawrence Douglas Wilder, 1990-1993
The Library of Virginia
35539
1.3 cu. ft. (4 boxes)
Virginia. Governor (1990-1994: Wilder)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The records must be reviewed by staff for personal and medical privacy protected information before serving.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from Governor Lawrence Douglas Wilder on 31 October 1996.
Biographical Information
Lawrence Douglas Wilder was born in Richmond, Va., on January 17, 1931. He graduated from Virginia Union University in 1951 and afterwards was drafted into the Army, where he served in the Korean War from 1952-1953 and received a bronze star. He then attended the Howard University School of Law and graduated in 1959. Douglas Wilder was elected to the Virginia Senate in 1969 as the first African American member since Reconstruction and served in the Senate for five terms. In 1985, he was elected to the office of Lieutenant Governor as the first African American to be elected to statewide office in Virginia. L. Douglas Wilder won the election for Governor of Virginia in 1989 and served from January 13, 1990 to January 14, 1994. He was the first African American to be elected as Governor in United States.
During the Wilder Administration, the Policy Office was headed by Walter McFarlane, Executive Assistant for Policy, and four Special Assistants: Richard Taylor (Health and Human Resources, and Education), Robert Blue (Finance and Natural Resources), Jeff Nuechterlein (Economic Development and Transportation), and Lynne Porfiri (Administration and Public Safety). The Policy Office was responsible for review and coordination of all policy matters, including: review of proposed legislation from agencies and Cabinet; formulation of the Governor's legislative initiatives; tracking legislation and serving as legislative liaison; review of General Assembly approved legislation submitted to the Governor for signature, amendment or veto; review of death penalty clemency requests, as well as other pardon and restoration of rights requests; review of legal settlements and other legal matters from the Office of the Attorney General's Office; review of proposed regulations; review of all matters pertaining to the judiciary and writs of habeas corpus; review of proposed executive orders; assistance with speech writing; serving as staff for Governor's special commissions; administrative support for Governor's Fellows program; serving as special interest liaison; acting as in-house counsel; and all correspondence with policy implications or pertaining to sensitive or controversial issues requiring legal overview.
Scope and Content
Records of the Policy Office: Extraditions and Writs of Habeas Corpus, 1990-1993, of Governor Lawrence Douglas Wilder. The records are organized alphabetically into 4 boxes. The Extraditions mostly contain memorandum from Walter McFarlane, Executive Assistant for Policy, detailing the name of the prisoner, the state which was requesting extradition, and stating the recommendation of the Attorney General. A few of the files include a copy of the extradition request and a prisoner profile. The Writs of Habeas Corpus include correspondence, prisoner profiles, memorandum, and a copy of the writ. The records must be reviewed by staff for personal and medical privacy protected information before serving.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged alphabetically by folder title.
Contents List
- Extraditions, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Extraditions, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Extraditions, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Extraditions, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Extraditions, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Writs of Habeas Corpus, 1990 January-June (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Writs of Habeas Corpus, 1990 July-September (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Writs of Habeas Corpus, 1990 October-December (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Writs of Habeas Corpus, 1991 January-March (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Writs of Habeas Corpus, 1991 April-June (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Writs of Habeas Corpus, 1991 July-August (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Writs of Habeas Corpus, 1991 September-December (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Writs of Habeas Corpus, 1992 January-February (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Writs of Habeas Corpus, 1992 March-May (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Writs of Habeas Corpus, 1992 June-September (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Writs of Habeas Corpus, 1992 October-December (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Writs of Habeas Corpus, 1993 January-February (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Writs of Habeas Corpus, 1993 March (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Writs of Habeas Corpus, 1993 April-May (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Writs of Habeas Corpus, 1993 June-July (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Writs of Habeas Corpus, 1993 August-December (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Writs of Habeas Corpus, Incomplete, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 3)